[Music]
hello everybody
nice to be with you
uh i wish you all a good good evening
for those of you who are in india and
asia a good day to those of you who are
in europe
and a good morning to those of you who
are in the americas it's great to be
with you all
on the 48th
live episode of ask abhijit
so let's see who all is with us i can
see many of you have been commenting i
can see karthik futuristic akash
knox prayash the real traveler tanmai
deshpande
shivaji rajeh aryan chohan satoru gojo
dragon power 50 s2 vlogs danish gurung
vidant shibani akshay erin kingster
pavan gautam
ultimate tiger prachu yugarwal hardik
sharma aj nayar prathik pratik
sangam tanmai
good evening good day to all of you
thank you so much for being here
so we gonna discuss whatever you ask me
any questions you have i will take them
up history geopolitics physics science
astrophysics quantum physics philosophy
you guys decide ask me questions i
answer them
so let's take a few questions
first of all i would like to tell you
that i do read all of your comments
i am no longer able to answer comments
individually because there are hundreds
of comments every day but i do take the
time every day
to uh try and read as many of your
comments as possible
like i said it's impossible to answer
them all but i try to read as many as i
can so i do hear you i do know what you
are saying and i appreciate all the
comments and all the inputs
and the opinions that you voice in the
comment section so please keep it coming
i do read them
right
so let's take a few questions now
okay
question number one is by
sankersham why i ha why are harappan
inscriptions not in sanskrit
so the answer to this is that we don't
know what language these inscriptions
are in because the script
has not been deciphered it has never
been deciphered there are many claims
by various
individuals of having deciphered the
script but none of those claims have
ever
withstood the scrutiny of uh independent
review for example there was this
individual called
mahadevan who claimed to have deciphered
the
the indus valley region script he said
it was the form of tamil or something
but i have read his papers they are
utter nonsense
so i am not saying it is this or that it
is
it's not this or not that my simple very
simple point is that the harappan script
the so-called harappan or indus valid
script has never been deciphered
and therefore we don't know
for sure
what language it represents
and therefore we cannot make the claim
that these inscriptions are not in
sanskrit or not in tamil or not in some
other language because we simply don't
know what language it is until it is
deciphered
so the focus the emphasis of researchers
or historians of our linguists of
scientists of
computer scientists etc the focus needs
to be first of all on deciphering this
script
and i believe i am i am very strongly of
the opinion that we need to use computer
science machine learning artificial
intelligence these new technologies in
trying to decipher the script because
clearly it represents one of the ancient
languages of india
some people claim it is tamil okay fine
i am i i
will take that claim seriously but it
has to be proven
and the most people i mean one group
says it is tamil or proto-tamil the
other group says it is sanskrit vedic
sanskrit or post-vedic sanctions or some
form of sanskrit well these two claims
exist these are the two major claims so
we need to decipher the script first and
try to see which language group or which
language family it matches
and only then can we make claims like
the it's not in sanskrit or it's not in
tamil or whatever right so the simple
point is it's never been deciphered thus
far and therefore we cannot say it's not
this or not that
i hope that explains
what where we are right now as far as
this
issue is concerned
right let's take a few more questions
okay
prithviram says recently the karnataka
high court declared that tipu sultan
fought with the british
so that he could impose the muslim rule
and he even did various horrific things
etc and what is my view about this my
view about tipu the
is very clear he was
a barbarian he was
a brutal
tyrant
that's what he was he was not a force
for any kind of good
he was someone who tried who spent his
entire life in career trying to destroy
indian culture and uh you know
and and he spent his entire career
oppressing the people of india he the
people he ruled over
there is absolutely
uh no doubt about this no question about
this yes in the past there has been this
narrative that has been woven around
this individual he has been portrayed as
a freedom fighter every year on republic
day or whatever
whatever the day is you have these uh
this display this parade in new delhi in
which the state of karnataka puts up the
effigy of this monster as if he's some
great uh
representative of karnataka i think
so you know what
this is all this has all been debunked
uh the narrative which mainstream
historians had put across for decades in
india all the textbooks also in india
used to say this is it's that he was a
freedom fighter who fought against the
british and there was even some some tv
series on the state-run television
television channel doordarshan wasn't it
the sword of tipu sultan in which he is
portrayed as a great freedom fighter who
fought for the country and died for the
country that's all lies it has all been
debunked he was a brutal
tyrant
and if the karnataka high court has
recognized this fact well i am glad it
has
because there is there was absolutely
nothing
about him that was good
he was an oppressor he was a tyrant he
was a brute he was a barbarian he was a
monster i mean i
can go on but you get the point so that
is
the fact about this specific individual
tipu
kalyan karthik asks despite
being the founders zod of humans why is
africa always left in the dark we never
read any african history
the west disposed of the entire
continent as a mere resource factory why
well that's what the west has done if
you study the history of the past 500 or
so years it's the age of colonization
so the west came um the west acquired
certain they developed and acquired
certain technologies
uh that enabled that allowed them to
navigate the whole world
via the oceans
and they developed these technologies
such as firearms etc which enabled them
to rapidly conquer other countries far
away countries the americas we know what
happened there a brutal horrific
genocide happened there
more than 100 million people native
americans died in north america itself
alone and even worse happened in
southern america in south america
and they colonized the whole of africa
they colonize most of asia we know what
they did in india they stole the they
plundered the entire wealth of india for
about two and a half three centuries
india's gdp was over one third of the
entire world's gdp and by the time the
british left in 1947 india's gdp was
less than two percent of the world's gdp
so we can see where the wealth went and
the british gdp rose while india's gdp
fell so it's very clear what happened
now when it comes to africa
in the 19th century
the european nations divided up the
entire continent of africa for colonial
purposes the germans were involved the
belgians were involved the italians were
involved to some extent the french had a
very great uh very very prominent role
in colonizing africa the british of
course were involved in this even the
americans were involved so they divided
up the continent and plundered
everything they could all the
natural resources all the mineral wealth
whatever was there everything uh it was
it is a horrific despirating
episode of history horrific because
africa had its own civilizations and
kingdoms very civilized very advanced
but
unfortunately all these uh
the thing about all the polytheistic
cultures is that they are very tolerant
they are very respectful of others they
are very accepting they are willing to
forgive mistakes and forgive
transgressions and all that
so that is a pattern that you see
throughout the past three five or three
or five centuries
that these monotheistic abrahamic
cultures have wiped out and destroyed
every polytheistic culture in the world
almost i think india is the only one
that stands now
the only and the oldest civilization so
this is what happened to africa africa
had
incredible
has an incredible history which has all
been wiped out
uh i think today uh native african
historians and writers are trying to
rediscover the history of africa
but uh
if they had any written records etc they
did have writing systems and all but
it's all been destroyed by the europeans
the same way the history of southern
america south america was destroyed all
the ancient texts of the
indigenous peoples in south america were
destroyed by christian missionaries
because they
considered that to be the work of the
devil or whatever that was the pretext
so if you destroy the native people's
history then you can impose your own
version of history on them and you can
impose your foreign religion on them so
that's what happened inside in south
america and north america that's what
happened in africa almost everyone in
these places in this in these continents
is almost exclusively christian now
the only uh region that
resisted
was asia to some extent india india is
still not converted
well there are conversions happening as
we speak right now but that's a
different story so that's the reason why
we never get to read any african history
because
all the records have been destroyed if
any existed all the kingdoms all the
empires all the civilizations all the
cultures have been totally wiped out the
almost the entirety of africa's
population is christian now or muslim
but there is very little very little
indigenous culture left yes there are
the various peoples there are various
ethnic groups like the igbos and various
other people the zulus and so on the
mantus
who to some extent
preserve try to preserve some aspects
aspects of their indigenous culture but
when it comes to religion they are
mostly all converted to one or the other
abrahamic religion
and so so that's the sad story of africa
it's the the place was plundered
destroyed and then discarded
and uh
we can see the consequences of that
today in the place
i mean today africa has been divided the
political boundaries of africa have been
all arbitrarily drawn by the european
powers so what happens is that you have
these ethnic groups that are spread
across multiple countries
ideally you would draw political
boundaries based on where each ethnic
group each linguistic group resides
now what happens is that you have two or
three countries across which an ethnic
group is divided for example the igbo
people or whatever
and their allegiance lies to their
ethnicity more than to the country in
which they reside
and therefore you have these horrible uh
outbreaks of tribal violence and and
much more and then you had what happened
in rwanda two decades ago which was all
done by the catholic church
they have actually officially apologized
for their role
in the rwanda genocide so even today you
have so much interference from the west
in africa
they will simply not let africa be in
peace and and develop on its own
so that's a brief uh
overview of what happened in africa and
what's still happening in africa today
it's it's a very sad story africa has i
most likely a history that's even older
than that of asia because
to the best of what we understand the
human species originated in africa
and later on it came out of africa and
spread in other parts of the world so i
think africa's history is the oldest
history and we know next to nothing
about it which is
which is a tragic tragedy
all right let's go to some other
questions
some other questions
okay so once again i have answered many
of these questions so in the so in case
i'm not answering your questions please
search my channel most likely most
likely you will find that the question
you have asked is
already been answered i have so many
short clips you can go through those
just search for for your question and
you will most likely find it
all right
akash asks
can putin vladimir putin be termed as a
modern day chanakya of geopolitics as he
has many achievements in chechnya
ukraine georgia syria afghanistan
venezuela
made germany and turkey take anti-nato
steps yes uh i would not say that mr
putin is a modern day chanakya but
uh
these these uh
policies and strategies that mr putin
pursues are nationalistic policies
uh they are these are policies that are
grounded in realism
not idealism they're grounded in real
politic and the only approach is
the the major approach is that of
pursuing the national interest of
russia
and that is very much the challenge this
school of thought that vishnu gupta
chanakya propounded
if you study his writings if you study
the arthashastra etc you will find that
he was very much a proponent of real
politic of realism
and of putting the national interest
above everything else so the duty the
highest duty
of a ruler
is to ensure the long-term prosperity of
the nation and the people so the ruler
is supposed to serve the nation and the
people
in a lot in the long term you may take
certain do certain things in the short
term that may not be well understood but
as long as it has the right long-term
effect it is all valid and legitimate
so the highest morality is that the
kingdom or the country or the nation
should prosper and the people should
prosper and i think overall if you look
at the entire
uh
career of mr putin as the president or
the leader of russia he has taken
actions that
promote
the russian national interest the
long-term national interest so he has
certainly expanded
done his best to expand russia's fear of
influence in the sphere of military
intelligence and other activities
in like you said he has
succeeded in pacifying the the caucasus
region dagestan chechnya
etc
he has taken certain actions in ukraine
he has reclaimed the crimean region
which historically has been a part part
of the russian empire so i think he was
he was
from his perspective justified in
annexing crimea using military means
when it comes to georgia also he has
furthered his national interest in that
region syria
he has
succeeded in defeating so to a large
extent nato and the us in syria
he he is now uh russian in interests are
now
uh playing out in afghanistan as well uh
in southern america also germany is
siding with russia when it comes to the
north stream pipeline the gas pipeline
and turkey is now
to a significant extent pro-russia even
though it is still officially a member
of nato so this is how the game of
geopolitics is played i mean you may
recall perhaps that just some time ago
just a couple of years ago maybe two
three years ago there was this incident
this military incident between turkey
and
russia in which the turks shot down a
russian fighter jet i think one or two
russian pilots lost their lives in this
turkish military action
and despite that
today turkey is more of a russian ally
not an ally of so
officially but
it is leaning more towards russia than
towards nato
so this shows how the game of
geopolitics is played you may have
certain setbacks in the mutual
relationship from time to time and yet
you have to overcome those setbacks and
look at the larger perspective what is
your larger national interest yes there
were certain problems the turks shot
down a russian plane couple of russian
pilots died now if it was indians they
would be all emotional and say we should
never work with them again
but mr putin is not emotional he thinks
he sees things from a larger perspective
from the national interest perspective
and that's why despite this
action by turkey
he was willing to reach out to turkey
negotiate with mr erdogan
and bring him to his side so that is how
you play the game of geopolitics through
realism through real politics and by
putting everything
subsidiary to the national interest so
yes mr putin can be said to be following
the teachings and the
principles of vishnu gupta chanakya
i have said this many times in the past
that it is a crying shame that india is
the one country in the world that does
not follow the teachings of vaishnav
even though the teachings came from
india from one of our greatest thinkers
it is countries like china and pakistan
and turkey and russia that follow the
chanakyan principles far better than
india so this is something that needs to
be rectified we need
i think in the past
decade in the past six seven years india
has become far better at its
geopolitical game and the kind of
politics in the kind of policies and
foreign policy we have i think we are
improving significantly
so
there is
certainly room for optimism
but it we need to get better at this for
sure
so
excellent question sir
right let's take a few more questions
and what are his contributions to bharat
to india at what time period the mauryan
empire existed late 4th century as the
mainstream says 1500 bce or some claim
how was it determined see the uh
the chronology of indian history is
still a matter of debate because the
entire chronology was created by the
british historians by the
colonial powers
and uh
there are clearly lots of flaws in that
it's
if you look at the official chronology
of india's history from the mainstream
history perspective it's as if there was
nothing in india no history in india
before 500 bce
there is not a single name of a king
that is published in print there's not a
single name of of a kingdom or empire or
republic or anything within india that's
published before 500 bce so it's as if
the mainstream historians have decided
there was no history in india before 500
bce
and if you look at the archaeological
record we find evidence
of archaeological settlements that go
back 10 000 years in india
extensive uh uh archaeological
settlements
you have the entire sindhu region which
has this incredible ancient urban phase
of india civilization the so-called
harappan or saraswati civilization phase
of india
and in various other parts of india also
we are now beginning to discover that
there has been an extensive networked uh
uh
networked settlements everywhere whether
it is in the ganga yamuna plain whether
it is in varanasi whether it is in
southern india khiladi and various other
places which we are now discovering if
even if you go all the way down to sri
lanka if you even if you go all the way
to kalinga magda which is orissa and
bihar even if you go to chandra ketu
bihar sorry
bengal
and even if we go all the way north to
the punjab region to afghanistan to
present-day pakistan we find settlements
everywhere
so what i am trying to say is that the
chronology of india's history is going
to eventually change as as proper
research is done
and that's why there are these questions
about when did the
when did various empires actually exist
in india
now some people claim that the actual
date of gotham buddha is about 1500 bce
not 500 or 400 bce right some people may
have made this claim some people have
called into question the dating of
vardaman mahavir the founder of the the
last great tirthankar of jainism and so
on
so i think this is all eventually going
to be rearranged the chronology as we
discover more things it's bound to
happen
now uh according to uh
the accepted versions of history the
mauryan dynasty uh was post buddha
sometime in the i think
fourth century or so bc approximately
right that's when it began that's when
vishnu gupta chanakya brought this young
boy chandragupta
to power he was an orphan boy he had no
lineage no aristocratic lineage or royal
lineage he was an orphan boy but
chandragupta maurya was elevated he was
tutored by the great strategist and
realist
vishnu gupta chanakya and he was
elevated to the status of emperor of all
india
incredible story and that's how the
mauryan empire began now who is lolita
i don't remember the exact century in
which he lived but he was one of the
great kings
of india i think he was based in kashmir
uh srinagar or somewhere thereabouts he
is the person he is the emperor who
who constructed the great marthan the
sun temple in northern india in kashmir
and he was a great conqueror
uh
mainstream historians try to deny this
but it seems from what we know from the
written records uh it it appears that he
conquered large parts of central asia
and large parts of
the rest of india as well so he was a
great conqueror he was
a very
vigorous military campaigner
and he most likely is one of the great
one of the great emperors of india
and i have said this in the past that if
you are a great emperor in india the
mainstream historians will try and
will try and marginalize your
contributions so so
there are many such great kings amo
ghawarsha
who i think was a rashtra empire emperor
if i am not mistaken i have remember
amogo versa
you have the cholas who until very
recently no one used to write about no
one spoke about in the until about five
years ago
i think about five years ago almost no
one in india knew the great achievements
of the of the chola empire they
conquered the entirety of southeast asia
all the way to the philippines right
so almost no one knew about this because
the mainstream historians would not
write about this there was there would
be no mention of the cholas
or the chalukyas or the rashtrakutas or
the satavahanas or any of these empires
and dynasties
in our history textbooks
so that's the
that's what's going to change now now
that history is out of the hands of
these
state-sponsored historians now that you
have independent researchers even
scientists who are now
studying and researching history now the
truth is
beginning to come out and it's going to
accelerate this process is going to
accelerate in the coming years in the
next decade or so
so what i would say is that
was one of the great emperors of india
and that is somebody that needs to be
studied in far greater detail
all right
okay i can see one question being asked
17 or 18 times which i will not take
let's see some more questions
okay here we are again uh my views on
audrey tushke i think
that
that person is not even worth discussing
see uh
i may have said this before let me say
it again i do not discuss individuals
individuals don't matter i do discuss
individuals who are
major historical figures
people who have genuinely changed the
world or contributed something
significant to the world i will discuss
such individuals i will discuss
vishnugov i will discuss
i will discuss
emperor ashok whether he was good or bad
doesn't matter he was a significant
figure i will discuss historical figures
napoleon alexander
julius caesar armenius
i will discuss historical figures and i
will discuss
prominent figures today who are
significantly changing the world that's
why i will discuss world leaders who are
still active today i will discuss
people like elon musk jeff bezos
uh et cetera
people who really matter now the person
uh
you just spoke about audrey trushki
is an insignificant person
50 years from today nobody will give a
damn about that person
so
i do not discuss such people i don't
discuss myself do i talk about myself
who is abhijit chavda what is his life
and career who cares
i am not that important i don't matter
so i do not discuss individuals it is a
matter of simple straightforward policy
that such people don't deserve
to be discussed so that's all i have to
say about that
right let's take some more questions
some more questions
now this is an individual i am willing
to discuss
yogi attitude i think he is a very
promising leader
i have a great deal of hope
in
in uh yogeji yogi adityanaji and i hope
that
once he has a
sufficient
uh
sufficient uh what do we call it
experience in administering a state like
up i hope that one day in the future not
in the very far future he may hopefully
ascend to the leadership of the country
i think there is a great deal of
potential in yukiji
and i hope to see that happen in the
future when the time is right so i think
i i think that he's one of the very
promising leaders in india today
right some more questions
someone asked me if i watch anime
japanese anime you know what i wish i
had the time to watch anime when i was a
kid i used to love watching cartoons
uh unfortunately as of today i do not
watch any anime i don't have the time at
all i wish i had the time to watch
certain such entertainment shows i used
to like anime yes but i no longer have
the time to watch it anyway what you're
saying is that please do a bookshelf
tour showing us your book collection
future video maybe hopefully i'll do
that in the future
this is not the only book collection i
have i have a whole stack of more books
i have two or three more bookshelves
like these
elsewhere and i have books lying around
everywhere so i have so many books i
have more books
i have
i buy more books than i can read and i
have read more books than i can i have
ever bought so that's
that's uh how it is with me and the
books
so these books here uh
many of these are all are about physics
i mean professional physics books uh msc
phd and further level and there are
other books as well over here about
i think history and philosophy and some
fiction as well
and i've got so many other books
elsewhere so maybe in the future i shall
perhaps make
it to a video about the books that i
have maybe
so yeah okay thanks for the suggestion
yes
all right what else do we have um
georgian ajayraj says please tell us
about the kalpa vigraha idol idol
you know i haven't studied this in
sufficient detail i have heard about it
there is this claim that it's an
extraordinarily old idol about 20 or 26
thousand years old or something i still
haven't found the time to study it in
detail so maybe give me a week or so and
i shall get back to you about this well
it's a good question thank you for
asking i shall study this in more detail
and then i shall get back to you about
this
uh spurs says is the government of india
really democratic or partial see the
democracy
let me tell you something
democracy is an illusion
whether it is india whether it is the
european union whether it is the united
states
all these liberal democracies they
to a large extent democracy
is an illusion it is a facade that hides
a deeper
reality
for so why do i say that democracy is an
illusion i think many of you will
disagree with what i am saying and i
understand why you will disagree because
aren't we all allowed to vote once in
five years isn't that the meaning of
democracy well i have some news for you
my friends
democracy is not only about voting once
in five years
the the true see there is something
called first principles thinking
there are two kinds of thinking one is
dogmatic thinking and one is first
principles thinking dogmatic thinking
means you have heard various
narratives from the media you have read
some articles you may have read a book
or two or somebody you admire in the in
the in the
as a public thinker as an intellectual
may have certain opinions and you
believe all that
and then when you when i say that
democracy is an illusion you will
reactively say that no you are wrong
because all these people have told me
that democracy is true and democracy
democracy is the best thing in the world
so that is called dogmatic thinking you
are thinking using the product products
of other people's thoughts
you are not thinking
from first principles so what is first
principles thinking
first principles thinking means going to
the root of the problem when i when you
talk about democracy first ask yourself
what is the meaning of democracy
voting once in five years is not the
meaning of democracy the true meaning of
democracy is that
since you have such a large population
in any country
you cannot all get together and run the
country therefore you
elect representatives who truly
represent
your
will
and those people will run the country on
your behalf but they have to be
answerable to you throughout
they have to be answerable to you and
they cannot run the country
based on their whims and fancies
the moment they try to do that they have
to be removed
so democracy has to be participative
and everybody
every citizen
should have an equal chance of becoming
an elected representative
and democracy has to be participating if
not just once in five when you vote once
in five years and then you forget about
it you're not participating in democracy
right so here's what happens in most
democracies
you vote once in five years then you
forget about it and then you have
no role in the governance or the running
of the country or in
influencing those whom you have voted
for
and the second thing is that
are you actually
are you actually capable of running for
election if you
if you want to stand for election do you
stand a chance
according to the theory of democracy
every citizen
has has the right to stand for election
and hopefully become a representative of
the people
so that is in theory and in theory in
india it is like that but in reality
you don't stand a chance of being
elected unless you have crores of rupees
to throw about in each election
so a common citizen doesn't stand a
chance of getting elected as an
independent candidate you have to become
a member of a political party and they
will choose you as a as they will give
you us
they will allow you to stand for
election
only if
you meet certain criteria now these
political parties
is there any internal democracy in these
i am not talking about any specific
party i am saying in general if you look
at the average political party in india
is there any internal democracy do they
vote for their leaders
or do they have a leader who is
do they have leadership that runs in
families
so the truth is that most political
parties in india
are
family run proprietorships there is no
internal democracy within
the members of the political party never
get to choose the leaders they can only
worship those who are in power in the
party
and that's why every them every election
year after your year you get the same
five or six candidates standing for
election
this is not democracy
this is a farce
first of all
in individual citizens don't stand a
chance if they start if they try to
stand for election
and secondly political parties have no
internal democracy and thirdly there is
no participation in democracy once you
vote
once the election is done you are
marginalized as a citizen you have no
say in what happens afterwards so this
is
why i say that democracy is fake
democracy has to be real there has to be
democracy throughout even within
political parties there need to be
transparent elections
for the leadership of the party
and so on
i think i need to
talk about this in further much detail
in a structured manner maybe i'll make a
video about this so this is not the
situation only in india
it's a situation in most so-called
democracies in the world
and that's how it is
so i would say to answer your question
the government of india is partially
democratic partially democracy it's not
a real
through and through democracy india is
not a through and through democracy no
country in the world is a real proper
democracy that's the answer that's the
truth
preet mohanty says what will happen in
world geopolitics if russia becomes more
powerful than the us well then you will
have a geopolitical realignment right
now the major power in the world
still is the united states of america it
has the world's largest and most
powerful military it has this global
network of military bases in various
countries across the world it has naval
bases it has a non-naval bases as well
it has airports it has access all over
the world and therefore it's a global
power it can influence
[Music]
events in the world at a moment's notice
that's why it's called a superpower
china is an aspiring superpower they
want to reach that status but they are
still far from it their
economic might is significant but now
their economy is
is showing signs of grinding to
a standstill which is a dangerous sign
for the world now when it comes to
russia i think it may not
i am not 100 sure but i think it's not
even in the world's top 10 economies or
maybe if it is it is somewhere near the
eight nine ten positions
most likely it's not in the top ten so
economically it's not that
powerful
russia's real power is its legacy
military
so when the ussr was a superpower it had
built up this military uh might it had
built up the means of of producing
military hardware
it developed all these technologies
whether it is rocket technology missiles
uh nuclear weapons
submarines
warships
fighter aircraft other kinds of aircraft
artillery tanks and so much more
so after the ussr collapsed everything
went into a decline but
when mr vladimir putin took over he
rejuvenated to some extent
uh the military machine of russia he
stopped the decline of the technologies
and and and the military uh
uh the armed forces and all that
he invested a lot in the armed forces
and that's why
the russian military is a genuine force
to be reckoned with despite russia not
being a very powerful and very big
economy and the other thing is that
russia has the world's largest arsenal
of nuclear weapons and ballistic
missiles i think their arsenal may be
larger than the arsenal of the us
so russia even though it's not a major
economy a very large economy it is still
i think the number two military power in
the world
it has the power to obliterate a country
like china if the need require is
required or even the u.s
but of course it will that that will
never happen one does not ever use
nuclear weapons
in the real world in in warfare it is
it is a deterrent and nothing else so
the question is what hap would happen if
russia becomes more powerful than the
u.s the russian military is
a very big
uh factor in this it is almost as
powerful as the u.s
military
uh when it comes to europe and asia
eurasia russia is i think
the most
prominent and most powerful military
force
in the continent
so it's already a very big power if and
i don't think russia has the ambition of
becoming a superpower again they are not
trying to construct military bases
across the world they're not trying to
do that they're not trying to project
power globally
i think they are the
their emphasis is on consolidating their
position position in eurasia
but if russia were to do that then the
world would become more interesting
there would be a tri-polar race then for
super powerdem u.s russia and china
and that would complicate matters
significantly
so that is all hypothetical but as of
today russia is a very major military
power and
maybe it's a stabilizing factor to some
extent because the world needs
some sort of balance if you have only
one superpower then that superpower can
run roughshod over the entire world when
you have two or three major powers then
it makes the world a more balanced place
but sometimes a more dangerous place so
that's how it is
prakash says if all humans have the
indigenous people of africa as their
common ancestors then how come then how
did different races come into existence
shouldn't we all have been black good
question so there is no such thing as a
race the the concept of race is an
outdated concept it's an unscientific
concept there is no such thing as a pure
race there is no such thing even as a
pure species
you know surprisingly enough
so these are uh
these are categories that were
constructed
by scientists i would say in the 18th
and 19th centuries the concept of race
the concept of
species etc
when science was very much still quite
rudimentary today we understand science
much more we understand molecular
biology we understand genetics
population genetics ethnography and much
more
so we now know that there is no such
thing as a pure race or a pure species
now how did so but your question is
still valid that the people of africa as
we know they are they all have dark skin
they are what we call the african
race or the black race so so to say
so how come people in different parts of
the world who are the product of and out
of africa migration how come people
across the world look so different
the people in eastern asia look
different the people in india in the
indian subcontinent look different
in iran the people in western asia look
different the people
in siberia
look different again the people in
europe are all also have a different
appearance different skin color
different eye color hair color so on
even in europe you have so many
differences if you go to scandinavia et
cetera you have people with blonde hair
very fair skin blue eyes mostly you go
to ireland you get people with red hair
you go to greece and in the
mediterranean region the people over
there have significantly darker skin
they are like like some people in india
actually the kind of skin color and hair
color eye color they have
etc so how come there is so much
diversity
in the human
species diversity of superficial
appearance
when we all came out of africa and the
reason for that is that people evolve
genetics evolves there is something
called natural selection
certain features are desirable when you
live in a certain climate
for instance if you're living in africa
where the sun is so bright especially in
the equatorial region
then it is beneficial for you to have
more melanin in your skin because
melanin blocks
much of the
energetic output of sunlight it blocks
the ultraviolet rays etc and it ensures
that you don't get cancer skin cancer
and other such
problems that's why when people live in
equatorial regions for
multiple generations maybe 10 20 30
generations they automatically
develop darker skin and similarly some
some effect would be visible in the hair
etc now when you move to northern
latitudes for instance in siberia in in
russia
or in mongolia et cetera
tibet
where the effect of sunlight is
significantly less than in the
equatorial regions
well in that case it is beneficial for
you
to have a lighter skin color because it
is only
when you absorb more sunlight that you
will be able to uh have sufficient
vitamin d
which is essential in the body for
absorbing calcium and developing strong
strong bones etc so that's why
uh
natural selection ensures that people
who live in northern latitudes
for multiple generations they are they
slowly start developing lighter skin now
if you live in
snow-covered plains etc where you have
this glaring sun
glaring reflection of sunlight into your
eyes then it is useful to develop
smaller eyes and that's how a certain
look appears over time and so on and so
forth when people live in india which is
neither very hot neither very cold
uh etc then you will develop a moderate
skin tone you know like the typical
brown
skin that you find in various parts of
the indian subcontinent
pakistan afghanistan even iran to some
extent and so on so that's how it
happens so it is because of natural
selection it's because of evolution
because you have to adapt to your
climatic and geographical environment
so we have been out of africa for about
70 80 000 years i think there is a
sufficient amount of time to develop all
these different
characteristics
and that's why we are not all black
but in the past people who lived in
europe were also black
for instance before the yamnaya invasion
of europe
you had various uh groups
of population groups in europe that had
very black skin
for instance the kromanian people the
cheddar man in the british isles
etc they had significantly darker skin
than
almost like today's uh
average african skin tone so you did
have that in europe in the past and not
in the very distant past but sometime in
the last 10 000 or so years itself
so
things change things change as human
migrations happen and so on and so forth
it's a complicated story but we are now
uncovering it thanks to archaeology s
and especially
genetics
right
tanmay says war has killed millions of
people so how would the world be like
with only peace well it would be a great
world but unfortunately the
the sad reality of the human species is
that we are a war like violent species
it is inherent in our nature the entire
history of humanity is a history of
warfare and conflict you find evidence
of conflict even in ancient africa you
find uh
they have recently discovered certain uh
burial sites in
eastern africa i believe
which seem to uh
be the earliest
archaeological evidence of warfare
you have people who clearly show uh
wounds
in their bones so
they died as a result of those wounds
and so on and they've been buried in a
certain manner so
what we know is that the history of
humanity is a history of warfare
human migrations
inevitably lead to warfare and conflict
and that is not only just something that
is characteristic to us humans our
closest relatives our cousins the
chimpanzees are equally if not more
violent than us they also live in groups
in social groups and these groups
from time to time come into conflict and
then there is full-scale war
and not just random
mob violence
calculated strategic planned violence so
the chimpanzees also do that it's been
observed and they are quite brutal so
that is something we share with our
closest cousins the chimpanzees we are a
war like
we are a violent species we are a
warlike species
we try to
uh go beyond these limitations
uh
but unfortunately it doesn't always work
for instance india has been a very
pacifistic kind of culture i know we
have also had conquerors and all but if
you look at
indian philosophy if you look at dharma
it is all about ahinsa parma dharma
non-violence is the greatest ideal
that's what we have tried to practice
but when you
become non-violent while others are
violent it doesn't work and that's what
we have seen in the past 1000 years in
india so it doesn't work unfortunately
it would be great to have a world with
only peace
but
our nature is such that we are greedy we
want more and more we want to control
more resources
across the world we want to control more
people across the world it's about power
it's about resources and that's all what
geopolitics is about
and that's why we simply don't have
peace
even right now we have certain conflicts
going on
in certain parts of the world
and the way the geopolitical environment
is shaping up during this decade it
looks like
something could go bad again
it looks like 1930s all over again right
now
so that's just the way it is it is in
our nature
that
we keep going to war we keep fighting
so that's how it is whether we like it
or not that's the fact of life
right let's
take some more questions
[Music]
now this is a question that's
interesting was mikhail gorbachev a good
leader who tried to save the ussr or was
he just a western puppet i think there
is a significant uh
there is
a significant opinion in
many parts of russia that mikhail
gorbachev was a western puppet
and
and well we do know that the ussr
collapsed under his watch while he was
the leader of the ussr so clearly he was
not strong enough or a good good enough
leader to keep the ussr together
he presided over the collapse and the
disintegration of the ussr
and then
he handed over in some way or the other
power i mean his his successor was boris
yeltsin who was very much
a western ally and under boris you'll
see in russia
ah it just
went so bad
it so it i mean the economic collapse
the people were in poverty
mauricio since uh reign as the leader of
russia was one of the lowest points
in russia in the past century or so
and it all happened thanks to the
actions of mr gorbachev whether it was
his actions or his omissions whether
it's acts of commission or acts of
permission doesn't matter
but
history will look at mr gorbachev as
somebody
who was unable to keep the ussr together
and
his actions led to what happened later
in the 1990s the all the near collapse
of the economy so i would say that mr
gorbachev was not a good leader
a country the size
of russia or the ussr needs a very
strong powerful leader i am not saying
the leader needs to be an autocratic and
oppressive or tyrannical leader but the
leader has to be strong enough
to be able to
to
hold the country together and administer
it
in the right way and the same applies to
india a country the size of india a
subcontinent-sized country
needs a leader of that magnitude
somebody with the force
of of will and character to be able to
take the country this enormous diverse
country in the in the right direction
it's it's a huge challenge
so i would say that mr gorbachev was not
it was one of the
weakest leaders the ussr ever so
wow
what book am i reading right now i'm
reading multiple books i am always
reading three four books in parallel at
the same time and i never have enough
time to read books
unfortunately
i have such a long reading list that i
need to read i think it's gonna take me
10 or 20 years to finish all those books
so it's all wishful thinking but
i'm always reading you can see a few
books here
and there are the books as well so i'm
always reading multiple books
aryan chakravati asks will countries go
back to invasion-like mode in the future
yes absolutely
it's the nature of the human species to
expand to have conflicts to go to war
right now we are in an age of relative
peace relative peace we sitting in india
are in peace
most parts of europe are peaceful north
america is peaceful
central america is problematic southern
america is right now reasonably peaceful
in all
africa has conflicts in various
places right now the world is relatively
peaceful but there is a lot of poverty
there is a lot of there are many
problems
artificially induced problems
but i think that in the next 10 years or
so we could see an upsurge in
what you call invasion mode
as the chinese economy
winds down as it grinds to a halt
which it is right now
i
it is possible the chinese leadership
could get a little desperate
and they would perhaps feel that while
they are still strong they should gain
as much territory
etc as possible and they may try to
indulge in certain military
misadventures it could start with taiwan
it would start somewhere else
but it is quite possible that they could
do something silly something stupid
if their economy shows further signs of
of
stalling so in the in the past the
chinese economy for the for the past two
three decades was growing at 10
plus
and that's what happens when you have
the right policies in a very poor nation
you grow very fast
today china has almost become a
middle-income nation
but now its economy is not growing
anywhere as fast as it was the official
figures are of about six percent growth
but that is the chinese communist
party's official figures which have to
be taken with a few grains of salt i i
certain
many experts
and geopolitical analysts
believe that the actual growth rate is
about one or two percent right now in
china so that is problematic very
problematic
and that could
cause some panic in china and it could
cause some rash decision making and then
we could have an invasion of taiwan or
or maybe the
japanese senkaku islands or maybe some
misadventure with india which would be
really stupid
or something in
something in china's north
east
manchuria etc where they have conflicts
historical conflicts with russia
and so on so there is a significant
potential for such things happening in
the coming decade
so yeah it's it's it's very possible i
hope it does not happen i want a
peaceful world we want to live in peace
but you never know
it's quite likely i would say
right
okay deer says i have read anuj book the
government doesn't want you to know this
he is an ex-journalist and
has researched for decades about about
sebastian
my comments so uh
i haven't read this book i haven't read
any of anujdar's works thus far
so uh i cannot comment as somebody who
has read his works but i agree with the
overall
uh the overall
understanding
i am i'm very i'm quite convinced that
subhashin rabos did not die in that
alleged plane crash in taiwan formosa
all those years ago
i
believe it is most likely that the
person known as gumnami baba was
actually subhashin rabos
who was forced
into anonymity in this manner by
possibly by the indian government maybe
the condition of for him to return to
india was that he would
not declare that he is watching the
rebels and he would go into some
anonymous mood somebody who never speaks
gumnami baba i believe there is a very
strong possibility that this is the case
so i do not believe the mainstream
narrative that subhashan durbose died in
that so-called plane crash i believe
that he
survived beyond the second world war and
i think i am
i think there is a very strong chance
that
gubynami baba was actually sebastian
rabos back in india i will need to read
uh mr anujar's works to
understand this in further detail
because i am aware of the fact that he
has done extensive research
in this topic so it is again something
that i need to read
a read up on
but my comment is that i
am quite convinced that sebastian rabos
did not die in that plane crash and most
likely he came back to india
okay tell us about the islamic golden
age was it built on the backbone of
indian science and technology so this is
something that
modern historians don't want to speak
about but if you look at the works of
the arabic historians and translators
such as
etc they are very clear
about the fact that they have merely
translated indian texts so let's let's
talk about what the islamic golden age
was
so it is something that went down for
about two or three centuries from the
from the 9th 10th 11th 12th century
thereabouts
and it was an age in which the islamic
world was quite liberal they absorbed a
lot of knowledge
from india because at that time india
was
under invasion by the turks
it started with
with the arabs under muhammad bin qasim
that's what is that's what we learn in
history but later it was the turks
who unleashed wave upon wave of invasion
on india
afghanistan was the first to fall
gandhar
the first part of india to fall to the
turkic invasions was afghanistan then
parts of punjab and so on it was a
gradual process which lasted about two
or three centuries or more than that
and what happened was that along with
the soldiers and invaders the
turks brought in
scholars from the islamic world people
like al-biruni and there are various
other writers so these individuals would
go to indian universities as you know
india was a land of education india had
so many great universities
and so on and so forth there are so many
you cannot even name them all in this
session so india had so many of these
great universities and they all had
these immense libraries which were all
eventually destroyed and burned in the
turkic invasions but while these
existed they still existed these islamic
scholars and translators would come to
indian universities they would
translate
books that interested them books on
astronomy books on pharmacology
toxicology medicine ayurveda
mathematics
uh strategy
uh
the pancha tantra the
jataka tales and so much more so they
translated all these texts from sanskrit
into arabic
and then they brought all that knowledge
back to the islamic world
at that time i think baghdad was the
center of the islamic world the center
of the caliphate
and these arabic histories were very
clear about the fact that these are
translations from sanskrit translations
from english from from sanskrit texts
one of these books was called kitab al
hisaba al-hildi
the book of hindi or hin or indian
mathematics
and so on so all of this knowledge and
see the thing was that there was no
copyright system at the time
uh
indians were very free with knowledge
we have always believed that knowledge
is supposed to be free it's not supposed
to be sold or or withheld
so
indian universities and professors and
scholars were very happy to allow these
guys to translate these texts into
arabic and then all of this reached the
islamic world
and it was used
to uh develop certain technologies
you had the cerec steel which was
produced in india
for about two and a half thousand years
that was also exported to the middle
east it is now called damascus steel for
some reason
uh and so on so all these technologies
made their way into the islamic world
all this
knowledge made its way into the islamic
world
and that led to this
renaissance of sorts in the islamic
world which is called the islamic golden
age and the islamic historians and
writers and translators did not ever
hide the fact that all this knowledge
came from india but when this knowledge
was transmitted to europe
the european
historians
decided to uh
to hide the true source of the knowledge
so the uh the decimal system was called
the arabic numerals for a very long time
today they are called the hindu arabic
numerals
these are just indian numerals there's
nothing arabic about them the only
arabic thing is that
it was transmitted from
to europe through the arabs not through
the indians and so on so
the arabs and the islamic writers never
tried to hide the fact that all this
knowledge was indian knowledge it is the
europeans who have hidden that knowledge
so today it looks like algebra
trigonometry calculus etc it all emerged
spontaneously in europe at the same time
and all
and so much more
so the islamic golden age was built on
the backbone of indian science and
knowledge and technology which is very
true and the islamic golden age came to
a sudden abrupt
halt
i think it was in 1258
when the grandson of ching is khan hula
ghukhan
invaded and destroyed baghdad in the
islamic world
so the islamic golden age came to an
abrupt
halt all of a sudden in
in the 13th century with the mongol
conquest
of baghdad
so that is a brief account of what
happened and what the islamic golden age
was
all right some more questions
so many questions let me pick up some
interesting ones
uh rathan
says my take on vaccines as not much
research is available they allowed it
for emergency used use
so this leaves us confused
see vaccines typically need to be
developed through an iterative process
you first develop a test vaccine you try
it on on
hapless animals if it shows good results
there then
and if it doesn't show good results then
you improve it you do something else you
make a vaccine that works on animals
then you try it on human subjects
a small group of humans if it works
there then you uh
do a second round with more
with more test subjects and so on so
it's a long iterative process there are
many failures there are many iterations
and and so on
so vaccine development typically takes a
long period of time it it is typically
not something that is rushed through and
and vaccines are typically not released
in a few months time it's typically a
few years two to five years i would say
at least
now in the case of the coronavirus
pandemic we had to develop vaccines very
fast
very
rapidly and so the process was kind of
compressed it was kind of rushed through
and therefore there is a great deal of
doubt among certain people
about the efficacy of the vaccine there
are many
claims of vaccine injury in some parts
of the world in the west especially
certain vaccines are considered to be
more dangerous by certain people and so
on
it is confusing for
lay people it's confusing even for
scientists who have not studied every
step of the process in detail
the thing is that i believe that the
indian vaccine at least is very safe it
is quite effective
so as long as you're in india i would
say go for the indian vaccine
it it it has a very high efficacy rate
and there is
almost no report of any adverse
reactions
i cannot speak about other vaccines
ideally we would have wanted a proper
long drawn out process of vaccine
testing and all that
unfortunately
it was not possible because we had this
new fangled virus that was unleashed
upon the world somehow
so yeah that's why you had a truncated
process of vaccine development i would
say that the indian vaccine is quite
safe i don't know about the chinese
vaccine i think it's not a good vaccine
at all it has a very
low
efficacy rate i believe and i don't know
about any other effects but the chinese
vaccine is something
which we don't use in india which is a
very good thing
i think we have two or three vaccines in
india the indian made vaccine the indian
developed vaccine
there's the uk vaccine and maybe
something else i would say just to be
safe go for the indian vaccine it works
all right what else
lots and lots of questions
yashwadeep says when will bharath unite
and form akanda bharat again what will
be the what would be the conditions or
circumstances for it
see the first thing i would like to say
is that bharat is not a geographical
region it is not a nation state it has
always been much more than a nation
bharat is a civilization it's a
civilization state and the
characteristic of a civilization is a
common unifying culture
so it's not about geography it's about
culture
you may have people of the same dna as
you but if they believe in a different
culture then they are not part of bharat
they are not part of a culture they are
not part of a civilization and that's
what we have in pakistan and afghanistan
these are now foreign cultures foreign
countries they are the same people as us
similarly for bangladesh the same people
as us
the same ancestry the same dna the same
shared heritage the
same shared history but today they
follow a foreign religion of foreign
culture
and therefore they cannot be part of
bharat
they are part of the historical
the historical region of of bharat
but
as long as they practice a different
culture they cannot be part of bharat
so i will i would say that it is
not possible for this dream of akanda
bharat to be realized at least in the
next hundred years
you can
conquer these regions militarily
yes and you can integrate them into your
country
by force
but these people
they are a different culture how are you
going to integrate them and assimilate
them when their beliefs
uh when when they have so much hatred
for you and your culture it doesn't work
right
so i would say that it is not going to
happen anytime in the next 50 years or
100 years it has to be a
multi-generational
project
and
what are the conditions and
circumstances in which bharat will
become will reunite again
well first of all india needs to become
a cultural economic and military
superpower
once again like it has always been
throughout history so india needs to get
to work
on reforming its internal system we need
to get rid of this fake western system
of governance
this inferior system of education
and all these colonial influences we
need to
rediscover who we really are
we need to rediscover our self-respect
we need to invest in science and
technology
no there is no progress without science
and technology just study indian history
the times when india was the greatest
civilization in the world was when india
was the most advanced scientific and
technological power in the world
so india needs to do all these things
once india becomes that powerful again
by the process of osmosis of ex-osmosis
india's culture will again start
influencing people beyond its current
geographical boundaries
and then the situation the circumstances
circumstances will again
come into place where you can have
an akanda bharath once again it's not
something that can happen in the next
10 20 50 years or 100 years i think it's
going to take longer than that
so we all have to play our role in this
it is a multi-generational
project
our descendants
should we should we should ensure that
we work hard enough and smart enough
so that our descendants
two three four generations down the line
are able to live
in a reunified india so that's what our
objective has to be we have to be
patient and we have to be confident
that's what we need
right all right
okay amal says what do you say to those
that the right-wing nationalists hired
you you know what
i wish somebody had hired me i wish i
was getting some funding a few lacks of
rupees
a month from right wing or any wing
i wish i wish i was on the payroll of
some some big organization i'm not
so all i would say is that you know what
i am not right wing or anything
i am
some people say i am
whatever they say you know what i am not
even a nationalist i am a
civilizationist
if i were to describe
my my belief my my worldview in in one
or two words it is indian
civilizationist i am not about right
wing or left wing or center wing or
anything
i i would like to see someday
india's civilization
regain
the status that it always had for
thousands of years that's the only
that's the only thing that i am
interested in
i don't care about right-wing
nationalists or left-wing nationalists
or
anti-nationalists or whoever else it is
i wish somebody was funding my work
unfortunately nobody is so that's just
the way it is
uh prithviraj says what is what are your
views on the practicing of reiki and
meditation so i am not familiar with
reiki i have never practiced or studied
reiki i don't know i think it is some
form of meditation or something i'm not
i don't have the specifics meditation is
great it is very beneficial but it's not
something that will give you results in
half an hour
meditation is hard
the first 5 10 15 times you try
meditation it's going to frustrate you
but only if you persevere
will you start seeing the real benefits
of meditation and again there are many
forms of meditation
some are
nonsense
some actually work
so you have to find the right
form of meditation that works for you
every human being is different what
works for you may not work for me what
works for me
may not work for a third person
everybody is different we are all unique
in our own way
we have to
find what works for us there are many
forms of meditation that all originate
in india you have vipassina you have
what they call transcendental meditation
uh
and and various forms of yoga even
pranayam is a form of meditation because
the very basis of meditation is
controlling your breath of course in
transcendental meditation there is no
emphasis on controlling your breath etc
it's all about clearing the mind of all
the noise the internal noise
it's about stilling the mind and
focusing the mind and that is very very
difficult my friends the mind is
an indomitable beast it is a noisy beast
it doesn't want to be tamed
so it's it's a struggle so if you i
would say meditation is very very
beneficial for anybody
but
it is very hard to do especially in the
beginning the first 5 10 15 20 times
it's going to be a struggle if you
persevere through that initial phase
then you will make significant progress
so
what form of meditation you should
practice is entirely up to you i think
there's all kinds of information
available online i would say go for one
of the forms ancient forms of indian
meditation whether it is
whether it is something as basic as
pranayama which also works as meditation
by the way
or it is something like the
questionnaire which is again very old uh
right
right now i think the buddhists have
tried to claim it fine okay claim it i
have no problem with that
and then there are various other forms
also
so i am familiar with vipassana and and
breath control which is pranayama etc
but uh and i have also tried what they
call transcendental meditation i think
you should try two three different types
of meditation and see what works
best for you i think it's something that
will benefit everybody
in their personal
growth and development
okay let's take some more questions
right good question neil says if netaji
was alive as gunnami baba then why did
he did he remain
hidden underground rather than forming
his own party and becoming the leader of
india
you know let's say that tomorrow i want
to form my own political party and be
the leader of india you think i will
succeed
i have
almost zero chance of success
what if someone wants to become
a leader of india and form their own
political party it's not an easy job
we have to understand what political
power is political power needs
mobilization of people people who will
follow you and obey you unquestioningly
and people who can take control of the
streets it's always that
behind political power there is actual
hard power
and for that you need
you need mobilization of people
you need this
invisible
infrastructure
this network of power that's what you
need to start a political movement it's
not an easy thing
so forming your party
okay theoretically you can form a party
but the moment your party becomes
significant in any way
you will
come up against very stiff opposition
from existing political parties who will
feel threatened by the emergence of your
party
and then you will re run into various
kinds of trouble
and as you know
if you look at the history of india
china etc
when there is political conflict
there is conflict on the streets there
is violence
and
and if you are a small political party
you think you can withstand that sort of
violence i mean just see what's
happening in bengal very recently
all i have to all you have to think
about is the events in bengal in the
past few months
to understand what happens when a new
political party comes up against an
established political establishment
now the thing is
why did subhashin rabos not reveal who
he who he was and why did he not not try
to start a political movement i think
see i am speculating here i am this is
pure speculation
if gomi baba was actually subhashin
rabos and he was allowed to come back to
india then there must have been
preconditions
imposed upon him by the neherubian
regime the first condition was would
have been you will never reveal who you
are the second condition would have been
you will never try to become politically
active
and
maybe he agreed to this and that's why
he was allowed to come back to india now
in case he he would have revealed who he
was and tried to start a political
moment i think it's very easy to get rid
of a person like that
politics is all about
about you know sometimes in politics
they eliminate people
i mean i know it's not a nice thing to
say but i mean
look at history
and that's it this is something that
happens routinely
if a new threat emerges politically you
have political assassinations and all
and it's happened so many times in india
so many there are so many instances of
political assassination and all that so
you know what these are the reasons why
subhash bashan rabos was not able to do
that in case gum nami baba was actually
him
then
all these restrictions were placed upon
him and the moment he would have tried
if he had tried
to reveal his identity and become
politically active he would have
disappeared overnight
so these are the hard realities of life
especially in politics and that's the
reason why
he was marginalized
i hope that the truth comes out
okay let's take some for some more
questions i already spoke about
already spoke about the kalpa vigraha
idol i will study it in further detail
and i will get back to you
sir um
okay rick says elon musk wants us to be
a multi-planetary species is it
necessary you know what it's not
necessary
i would say
i i don't i am not against us becoming a
multi-planetary species i would love
that
but it is not necessary
as of today it is good to have
and let me tell you why so first of all
one of the arguments that is given
as to why we need to start colonizing
other planets is that our planet is
dying
we have ruined it totally we have messed
up the environment we have polluted all
our water bodies now we have we are even
destroying the oceans with all this
plastic
pollution and various other assorted
garbage and sewage we are dumping into
the oceans
uh
so we have we have caused so much
deforestation now we have caused climate
change
the global temperatures are slowly
rising
and it's going to cause global warming
it's going to cause the sea levels to
rise we're going to lose our coastal
cities and settlements and on
so we are on the brink of a natural
catastrophe it looks like something that
will happen in slow motion over the next
100 200 years
and therefore maybe it's go it is
necessary for us to move to mars or some
other place so that is one of the
arguments that's put forth i would say
it's a stupid argument that is not the
right the reason why we should go to go
and explore the planets
earth is our forever home it is our
birthplace we cannot trash it and then
move on
this
this entire idea of crashing
your planet and moving elsewhere
it is something that comes out of
european colonialism
so what the europeans did in the past
500 years was that they
invaded entire continents north america
south america africa asia and they
plundered everything they treated
everything as a resource
they treated mother earth
as a repository of resources something
that is to be exploited
and they caused immense ecological
damage if you look at north america
today it's you i mean
the entire
mentality is a settler mentality
that we are here temporarily this is a
country or land we have conquered we're
gonna use it we're gonna exploit it
and we're gonna trash it look at what's
happening look at the fracking that's
being done it is it is causing so much
harm to the environment it is polluting
uh groundwater resources almost like
forever and so on and they just don't
care they just want to exploit resources
and use them and then move somewhere
else so this entire mentality
of trashing your home planet then moving
somewhere else
it's it's a consequence of the colonial
mentality uh that has been invoked for
the past few centuries
now if we destroyed our planet and moved
to mars what is the guarantee we will
not destroy mars in a few hundred years
again
so that is not the right uh
reason for moving to another planet but
i would say that it is very much
worthwhile
for us to become a multi-planetary
species
because it gives us more options in the
future if something happens if if we
discover a comet or an asteroid that is
headed for earth
then as of today we do not possess the
technology needed to divert an asteroid
or a comet which would possibly lead to
the end of humanity so in case we have
another planet where we have been able
to settle down it will give our species
a chance we may even be able to move
some more people to
mars or wherever else before such
an impact happens so that is one reason
why we would want to
become a multi-planetary species the
other reason is that it
it helps us build better technology and
it gives us more options
eventually hopefully
we should become a species that
exists on multiple planets planets maybe
even on multiple star systems if we can
move to al to the alpha proxima centauri
star system or something in the next
couple of hundred years or so it will be
good
so progress scientific and technological
progress is always welcome we have to
keep progressing but it doesn't mean
that we should treat our home planet as
a disposable
resource
so
i am i agree with elon musk to a great
extent we should become a
multi-planetary species but
it should not come at the cost of
destroying our home planet
okay let's take some more questions
okay this is an interesting uh
interesting observation by kalyan
karthik
kalyan says karthik says that as a
telugu speaker i can vouch for the fact
that telugu has at least 50 shared
vocabulary
with sanskrit but telugu is in the
so-called dravidian language family rip
logic what are my thoughts
i agree with you you know this entire
language family the so-called dravidian
language family was created by an uh
british missionary was it
was it robert caldwell i think it was
robert caldwell who studied one southern
indian language tamil
and on the basis of his fragmentary
rudimentary understanding of just one
language he created an entire language
family in which he placed telugu kannada
malayalam tamil and various other
southern indian languages
and our historians and linguists and
academic experts
blindly slavishly have been following
this nonsensical categorization ever
since
it tells you it shows you how deeply
mentally colonized and mentally enslaved
our academicians
are
so like you say
the telugu language has at least 50
percent shared vocabulary with sanskrit
it is easier for a person whose mother
think is telugu to understand sanskrit
than it is to understand hindi
and the same can be said about languages
like like kannada for example which also
has about 40 to 50 at least of shared
vocabulary with sanskrit there is a
significant amount of sanskrit
vocabulary in malayalam in tamil and
every other southern indian language
and yet it's called the dravidian
language family i am not saying that
that we don't need to properly examine
the languages what i would like to see
is that we need the government of india
should start
a national institute of linguistics
in which they would appoint young
researchers not established once young
researchers in their early 20s
a bunch of researchers 10 20 30 40 50
researchers who would spend the dedicate
the time to researching india's
linguistic
families a priori from the very
beginning without any of these colonial
influences
and only then will we be able to study
and understand
our
ancestral linguistics properly right now
like i said we don't have first
principles thinking we have dogmatic
thinking our thoughts are all predicated
on what nonsense has been poured into
our heads since the time we were born we
don't think a priori we don't think from
first principles so that is something we
need to start
so kalyan karthik you are absolutely
right there is no logic in placing
telugu in the so called dravidian
language family there is no such thing
as a dravidian family the word dravidian
is a colonialist
colonial invention
it is something that was derived from
[Music]
some word
uh
i don't remember which word it is but if
you look at india's classical rich
literature in any language
that is more than 500 years old there is
no word like dravidian or dravida
this is a colonial invention
it the word dravidian is is
derived from some word that they had
found somewhere in india's literature
but it isn't it is a it is a neologism
that's what it is
so
i agree with you karthik that this needs
to be re-examined
a priori
from first principles
now this is a good question what's the
difference between culture religion and
nation culture is is
an entire manifestation of your
lifestyle
the languages you speak
the traditions
you follow
and practice
the kind of lifestyle you have the kind
of world view you have
the festivals you celebrate the kind of
music you enjoy and
the kind of music that has emerged out
of your
out of your
civilization
the kind of entertainment and art forms
you have the dance forms
and the kind of education
uh system you have what kind of uh
what kind of ethics and morals
uh you follow
and and um
and revere kind of you know and and and
what gods you worship
what is your philosophical outlook and
on and all of that is what constitutes
culture
so when we talk about
dharma
the various dharmic traditions hinduism
buddhism jainism
and much more
there is actually culture
it is a manifestation of culture and
civilization it is not a religion
it is not religion what they call
hinduism
and sikhism jainism these are not
religions these are dharma
the translation of dharma is not
religion dharma is a word
that cannot be translated into english
because in english is a narrow inferior
and limited language
it is not a nuanced language
so
what is religion religion is one of the
three abrahamic belief systems
one god one prophet one book
there are three abrahamic religions so
religion is that only
no polytheistic belief system can be
categorized under the under the umbrella
of a religion it is different its
culture its its civilization
so that is culture that is religion and
nation is simply a geographical entity
a geographical entity
in which you so it is the it is
something that comes out of the treaty
of west valley a few centuries ago
so today we follow the westphalian
nation-state system in which every
nation is a specific geographical area
in which you have a number of people who
live there and you have a specific form
of governance
so that is a nation and each nation is
supposed to be sovereign and there
should be no interference and so on and
so forth according to the theory which
never actually happens in reality it is
not implemented in practice there is a
lot of
interference and attempts to undermine
nations over indian zone
so india is today defined as a nation
state
which is an enormous fall
from its historical position which is
that of a civilization state
so in a civilization you can have
multiple political entities you can in a
civilization you can have multiple
kingdoms
multiple nations
so if you look at the extent of india's
civilization historically it has been
the entirety of india's subcontinent
and much of southeast asia
much of china is influenced by indian
culture historically tibet was part of
india's civilization and japan also to a
great extent is influenced by indian
culture so civilization is something
that is much broader
nation is something that is very
truncated and restricted
religion is an abrahamic construct and
culture is what i just explained in
brief
so good question
very interesting username
the question is why did the why
were martial arts wiped out from india
at the national level
while they survived and remained in
other parts of the world how to revive
it see you know what
whenever a country or a nation
comes under foreign occupation
under the occupation of a brutal
tyrannical
regime
then the first thing they do is to try
and stamp out
all possibilities of native resistance
so when the turks invaded and occupied
india they did their best to stamp out
indian resistance
and therefore the best thing to do was
to try and ban and wipe out india's
indigenous martial arts
india had a very ancient very rich
tradition of martial arts
today the only few things that remain
are what remains of shastra vidya in
northern india
there is a dance in saurashtra in
gujarat which is all that remains of the
ancient rajput tradition of sword
fighting
then you have kalare payotu in
in kerala which is one of the old forms
of india's martial arts and then you
have
a martial arts tradition in manipur
which the british also tried to stamp
out in the from 1891 onwards but some of
it has survived and it's very
interesting so it's in manipur it's
called
and there is another form of martial
arts also in manipur
now you can you see that martial arts
have survived in burma in thailand in
the philippines
in indonesia as well in burma you have a
form of martial arts in thailand you
have uh muay thai
in philippines you have
what do you call it silat i think
in indonesia you have kali
in korea you have taekwondo in japan you
have
you have karate dough you have aikido
you have ninjutsu and so on
and in china you have
you have
kung fu
now as we know i hope you know
kung fu is indian in origin it is an
indian
uh monk and scholar
bodhi dharma who traveled to china
and introduced this ancient indian
system of
unarmed combat to china in the shaolin
temple which was built for his
predecessor
and that is what the chinese took forth
and developed further over the centuries
and it is now called kung fu
so
most of asia's martial arts are
influenced by kung fu whether it is
whether it is taekwondo or many other
things
so one could say that
many of in of asia's martial arts
owe their ancestral lineage to an
ancient indian martial art that is no
longer in existence
so the reason why we no longer practice
our martial arts is because of the past
1000 years of foreign occupation of
india in which these foreign occupiers
did their best to eradicate india's
martial culture
so how do we revive india's martial arts
so we can try and uh
create
schools of various martial arts for
instance we have shastra vidya in
northern india which is all about armed
combat which is not something very
practical to revive because you may get
hurt doing that
even if you look at the rajputic
sword fighting tradition that is
something that one can't really revive
because indians are no longer allowed to
carry swords
what can be revived is to some extent uh
kalari payutu which
does involve unarmed combat it also has
sword and shield fighting
so kalori pyotr can be revived when it
when it comes to the unarmed combat
tradition and the manipuri martial arts
are very interesting they should also be
revived and you can have nationwide
tournaments of various martial arts and
that would be interesting i would say so
that is one way one could revive the
martial arts in india
right let me take
one more question
[Laughter]
is a zombie apocalypse possible in real
life so the so once again if you look at
first principles thinking what is a
zombie a zombie is a person who has died
physical death and then somehow that
person is revived
so according to everything we know about
science it is not possible for a person
to be revived after the body has died of
physical death
and therefore zombies the according to
the classical definition of zombie that
that is not
medically
possible
so i would say that a zombie apocalypse
is not really possible in real life but
yeah you can have certain diseases that
may feel like a person has kind of lost
their mind and become like a zombie or
something that is
technically theoretically possible but
the classical zombie apocalypse of the
movies like world war z and all nah that
doesn't really that's not really
possible in real life
shall i take one more question
okay this is the last question for today
from rahul pandey was india at around
800 1000 a.d a buddhist majority country
how did we revert the demographic you
know what the thing is this there is no
such thing i have said this a hundred
times i will say it a thousand times
more
this categorization of indian
religions
into hinduism buddhism jainism sikhism
is a foreign concept
the british decided to divide and rule
india therefore they tried to divide
india's population and create divisions
by creating divisions between both the
dharma and other dharma between jaina
dharma and dharma and so on
buddhism jainism sikhism hinduism etc
are the same thing they have the same
ancient
origins
they have the same fundamental concepts
what you are told is the is that
buddhism doesn't build there is no
concept of
of soul of atma in buddhism
that is a lie
and it is also told it is also it is
also told that
buddhism does not recognize the validity
of the vedas which is once again a lie
look at my older videos you will find
the truth there i have given references
so now to answer your question yes about
a thousand years ago or so
there was a significant
what we call both the dharma which is
one of the flavors of dharma itself was
very popular in india it was quite
widespread
what happened
how come it is not practiced anymore in
india
it is all a consequence of the turkic
invasions of india so the turks when
they invaded india they started from
central asia central asia was hindu
buddhist all of it even today you will
find ancient hindu temples all across
central asia even in armenia azerbaijan
and you will find buddhist stupas all
across central asia in uzbekistan
turkmenistan
azerbaijan so on and so forth kazakhstan
everywhere
so the turks what they did was
they destroyed the eradicated buddhism
from central asia they destroyed all the
supers all the monasteries all the
temples
and they destroyed as many statues of
the buddha as they could so the the word
for idol or statue in these people's
vocabulary was bhut
which means buddha
and when they started invading india
starting from gandhar which is
afghanistan
they started destroying every
manifestation of both that they could
find so they destroyed all the ancient
universities
all the ancient
stupas viharas monasteries etc they
massacred buddhist monks
and
they destroyed buddhist
statues and so on so their aim was to
destroy every manifestation of both of
buddhism of
and that's why their primary emphasis as
they conquered more parts of india also
destroyed buddhism what they considered
to be
the the
religion of the infidels
so it is
the consequence of the turkic invasions
that buddhism or or this specific flavor
of dharma was wiped out from india
because all the teachers all the monks
were massacred all the libraries were
destroyed the libraries and the
universities taught all flavors of
dharma not only buddhism okay
when you talk about nalanda university
which we know burned for three three or
six months
it did not only teach buddhism it taught
the vedas also when we talk about great
scholars like nagasein naga nagarjuna
etc
who went to china japan etc they did not
only teach buddhism they also taught the
vedas
so but the turks wanted to destroy all
manifestations of buddha
and that's why they succeeded
in wiping out what we now call buddhism
from india that is how this demographic
what you call
was eradicated from india it was done by
the turks about a thousand years ago
and that is the story
all right my friends
that is it for today
thank you very much for all your
questions and i am going to end this for
today i will do two more sessions next
week and it will continue every week
so i will see you very soon my friends
thank you everyone thank you everyone
for all your questions for your
participation for your support and i
will see you soon
thank you good day and good night